# 現在帶大家看一下那個花竹鼠 長得多大啦 (註︰這個「花」和「小花」想了很久喔)
Now let me show you the tinted bamboo rats. Let's see how big it is.
# 感覺天天看著它
It doesn't seem to be growing too much to me,
# 長不大的一樣
as I see it every day.
# 這個 這個辟邪的
Its, it's for warding off the evil power.
# 這個 小花
This is, little Tinty.
# 大花 不是小花啊
It's big Tinty now, not little Tinty.
# 你叫大花啦 那麼大條
I should call you big Tinty now. You're so big already.
# 很乖的哦 這個
It's really nice and gentle, this,
# 花竹鼠
tinted bamboo rat.
# 給它發一個很曲條的老婆 哦
I've given it a very slim wife, right?
# 呵呵 誒 你不能抓我
Hm hm! Ey! You can't scratch me!
# 很靚吧
Isn't it beautiful?
# 它的後代有好多啦
It has a lot of offspring now.
# 有 將近十多只誒 (註︰十多似乎是十三以上，dozen只有十二，所以改一下字眼)
There are, around a dozen of them.
# 這個是公的哦
This one is male.
# 現在毛都有點黃啦
It's coat is a little bit brown now.
# 你看它的牙齒
Look! Its teeth,
# 從它的牙齒上就可以判斷它
I can say from its teeth that,
# 很健康
it's very healthy
# 我去看一下它的崽
I'll take a look at its children.
# 崽在那邊
The children are over there.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個就是
This is, I mean,
# 小花的
Tinty's
# 大兒子
eldest son.
# 你看 都長那麼大了它
Look! It's already that big now.
# 好好長身體哦
Grow healthily, alright?
# 將來我發個老婆給你
I'll give you a wife in the future.
# 它現在一個人住
It's now living alone.
# 還沒長大 要它長大了再說
It hasn't grown up. I need to wait until it grows up.
# 身材
Its build,
# 很好哦
is really nice.
# 還有
There are more.
# 這個 小兒子
This is, its little son.
# 你看
Look!
# 這是它的小兒子
It is its little son.
# 也是公的
It's also male.
# 像你老爸
You look like your dad.
# 呵呵
Hm hm
# 拎著它 哈哈哈
Holding it, ha ha ha!
# 肚子怎麼那麼大
Why is the belly that big?
# 吃得很多的喲
It must have eaten a lot.
# 幸好你是花的
You're so luck that you're tinted.
# 要不然就把你賣啦
I would have sold you otherwise.
# 不要咬我啊
Don't bite me!
# 咬了我
If you bite me,
# 我就把你那個啦
I would have you, you know what I mean.
# 很靚啊 這個 你看
It's really beautiful! Look!
# 它尾巴
Its tail,
# 肉嘟嘟的
is so meaty.
# 呵呵
Hm hm
# 還有一個 還有個它兄弟 更漂亮哦
There's one more, it has a brother, which is even prettier.
# 你去看一下
Let me take a look.
# 在那個池子
It's in that cell.
# 這個也是它兄弟
This is also its brother.
# 也是公的
It's also male.
# 肥嘟嘟 你看 縐紋都出來了有 (註︰這裡應該不能用"Wrinkle"，不是這意思)
Chubby chubby. Look! Its skin is even folded.
# 很乖呀 啊
It's so nice, ah!
# 沒事 我看下哇 跟大家打個招呼
No worries! I just take a look. Say hi to the audience!
# 你看 它肚子 很飽滿哦
Look! Its belly, is stuffed.
# 吃得多
It eats alot.
# 耶 放下去
Ye, put it down.
# 再去看一下 還有 這裡一個
Let's see the others. There are more. One is here.
# 這個 肯定是它的
This one, must be its,
# 稍微小一點的 小兒子
it's a bit smaller, its little son.
# 也是那個是小的
It's also the little one.
# 你看 這個
Look! This is,
# 去去 又是公的 (註︰「去」應該是象聲詞)
chu chu, it's also male.
# 全是公的 哦
All are male, oh!
# 跟它老爸一模一樣
It's exactly the same as its dad.
# 呵呵
Hm hm
# 這個稍微比較短一點 這個
This is relatively a bit shorter, this one.
# 這個
It's ah...
# 這個到時候 看一下
Let's see later,
# 它的身材怎麼樣
how its build becomes.
# 不行的話 我們
If it's not good, we'll,
# 拿來當 當做商品鼠
take it as, as a product rat.
# 處理 (註︰這樣斷句不能翻譯，換成其他沒太大意義的字算了)
I mean,
# 當做肉鼠來處理你
We'll take you as meat product.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個終於有一個母的啦
This is finally a female.
# 這個就是母的
It's female.
# 好好下崽哦
Give good birth to babies, alright?
# 好 好兇啊 母的就是不一樣
It's so, so fierce. The gender makes a difference.
# 比較兇
It's more fierce,
# 像女的一樣 好兇
like a woman, so fierce.
# 啊 這個最漂亮的在這裡
Ah! This is the prettiest and it's here.
# 在這裡 你看 這個
It's here. Look! This one.
# 你看這個樣子 一身白的
Have a look at it. It's white all over the body.
# 它這個毛色很靚
The coat is really beautiful.
# 它的尾巴是黑的
It has a black tail.
# 它不聽話 它想咬我
It's naughty. It wants to bite me.
# 這樣不行哦 這樣
It will be a problem, you know.
# 哎喲 把它掐著就好啦
Ayo! It's alright now when I'm grabbing it.
# 不聽話
Naughty!
# 我掐你脖子哦
I grab your neck, eh!
# 我掐你這個 等下你咬我 我不掐著你
I grab you here. You would bite me if I didn't grab you.
# 它這裡
Hold it here.
# 越漂亮越不聽話
Prettier means naughtier.
# 這可以哦
It's not bad.
# 額 這個
Eh, this one,
# 也是公的哦 這個
this one is also male.
# 放在這裡
Put it here.
# 你看 這個
Look! This one,
# 這個比小胖還 還胖 這個
this is even fatter, fatter than Small Fatty, this one.
# 它很長哦 小胖比較胖一點
It's rather long. Small Fatty is a bit fatter.
# 很長條 這個是種公鼠來的
It's very long. This is a sire rat.
# 肉質很好的哦 這種
The meat of this kind of rats has an excellent texture.
# 它不聽話
It's naughty.
# 它一宜嗒嗒嗒嗒的響
It's making the sound "tak tak tak tak".
# 想 它想咬 哦
It, it wants to bite me.
# 屎都嚇出來啦
The poop is being scared out of it.
# 以為我把它拉去幹嘛
It thinks that I might be taking it to do something not so good.
# 放心啦 不會的
Don't worry. I won't.
# 這些比較瘦一點
These are a bit more skinny.
# 你看 這個 這個是
Look! This is, this is,
# 這個 這個是那個
it's ah, it's, I mean,
# 那 那個花竹鼠的孫子 你看
the, the grandchildren of the tinted bamboo rat. Look!
# 好小哇
It's really small!
# 好靚哦 現在
It's so beautiful now.
# 這個是母的哦
It's female.
# 這是最小的 這兩隻
They're the smallest, these two.
# 這裡好大 吃得好飽
It's so big here. It has eaten a lot.
# 這還有一個
There's one more,
# 還有個小的
a small one.
# 小的比較瘦一點
The small one is a bit skinny.
# 這小的比較瘦一點
This small one is a bit skinny.
# 它身材很好哦
It's build is really nice.
# 你看 還有那個 細小的絨毛都長出來啦
Look! There's also the, the fine fluff coming out.
# 冬天 長了這個絨毛的話就不冷
During winter, it won't feel cold with the fluff.
# 應該剛斷奶沒多久的
It should have just weaned.
# 你看 這邊都已經把那個竹鼠全部養滿啦
Look! The cells here are all fully utilized.
# 這每個池子都有
There's a rat in every single cell.
# 還沒給它們配種
But I still haven't let them mate.
# 到時候
Later, I'll
# 給它們發老婆
give them wives.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我要回去煮飯啦
I need to go back and cook.